Guide to the Vernon-Benshoff Company Records, 1911-1972 AIS.1972.06
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Vernon-Benshoff Company Records
1911-1972
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Vernon-Benshoff Company
AIS.1972.06
1.25 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
The Vernon-Benshoff Company was established by Harold and Lester Vernon, along with their partner, William Benshoff, in 1922. The Company records include tapes and transcripts of the history of the company, details about the development of the dental base Vernonite, alloy specifications for the casting metals, business accounts and correspondence, legal papers, various price lists, photographs, memorabilia, some outside publications, and The Vernonite Work Bench.
History
The Vernon Gold and Refining Company was chartered to Harold and Lester Vernon on December 15, 1915 in Pittsburgh. Most of their metal refining was for the purpose of making dental supplies. When a bank coalition forced the brothers out of business in 1922, they established, with William C. Benshoff as a partner, the Vernon-Benshoff Company in 1923. The company developed various casting metals, including "Chilcast," a dental base made of monomeric and polymeric methacrylic resins, a process of imbedding objects in acrylic for decorative purposes, and material for orthopedic appliances. The company continued after Mr. Benshoff died in 1935. Around 1945, the Vernon brothers were involved in the trial of the DuPont and Rohm Haas companies, which were charged with forming a cartel; eventually the charges against the Vernon brothers were dropped. Lester retired in 1955, but Harold continued to act as a research consultant for the company until 1962. The Vernon-Benshoff Company became a subsidiary of C. M. P. Industries, Inc., of Albany, New York in 1972.
Scope and Content Notes
The Records of the Vernon-Benshoff Company are arranged into ten series: History, Technical papers, Price Lists, Contracts and Legal Papers, Accounting Records, Correspondence, Publications, Memorabilia, Photographs, and Miscellaneous Writings. These records include tapes and transcripts of the history of the company, details about the development of the dental base Vernonite, alloy specifications for the casting metals, business accounts and correspondence, legal papers, various price lists, photographs, memorabilia, some outside publications, and The Vernonite Work Bench. Complete series descriptions are included before each series listing.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Harold Mark Vernon on June 14, 1972.
Previous Citation
Vernon-Benshoff Company Records, 1911-1972, AIS.1972.06, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Vernon-Benshoff Company Records, 1911-1972, ais 72:6, Archives of Industrial Society, University of Pittsburgh Libraries
Business and Industry; Biomedical materials -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Dentistry -- Research -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Industries -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Vernon, Harold M.; Vernon-Benshoff Company
- History, 1972; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I is comprised of four audio cassette tapes and three folders of transcripts. The tapes, which are housed in a folder at the beginning of Box 1, contain recordings of interviews with Harold and Lester Vernon regarding the history of their companies; the folders contain transcripts of these interviews. The Vernons discuss the founding of their companies, former employees, the Vernonite process, and key events in the history of Pittsburgh. The audiotapes are arranged in order from 1 to 4, and the transcipts are arranged within folders in the same order. Folder 3 contains the transcripts of interviews for which there is no corresponding audiotape.
  - Typed transcript of interviews on tapes 1-3, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Typed transcript of interviews on tape 4, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Typed transcipts of miscellaneous interviews, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Technical Papers, ca. 1922-1953; II.
  Series II contains reports and notes on the testing and physical properties of certain alloys. These materials include a notebook compiled by Harold M. Vernon, papers describing alloys used by Vernon-Benshoff and its competitors, reports, and reprints from the Journal of American Dental Association. The materials in this series are arranged chronologically and then alphabetically within the folder.
  - Vernon, Harold M. Lab notebook, ca. 1922-1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Papers on the physical properties of alloys, ca. 1930-1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Reports on techniques used by other companies, 1931-? (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Price Lists, 1928-1950; III.
  Series III contains lists of various alloys from 1928 to 1950. The lists are arranged chronologically within the folder.
  - Lists of various alloys, 1928-1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Contracts and Legal Papers, 1939-1945; IV.
  Series IV is comprised of legal materials pertaining to the Vernon-Benshoff Company and its practice. The first folder contains contracts with the Rohm Haas Company and the University of Illinois's College of Dentistry for the study of the resilient synthetic resins. The second folder contains subpoenas related to the U.S. District Court case with the Rohm Haas Company. The materials are arranged chronologically by folder.
  - Contracts, 1939, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Subpoenas, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Accounting Records, 1911-1949; V.
  Series V contains financial materials created in the course of business of the Vernon-Benshoff Company. These materials include various accounts, a ledger book, statistical data on dividends, securities, and number of employees and payroll, profit and loss statements, and miscellaneous items pertaining to insurance policies, vouchers, and securities. Except for the miscellaneous items, all materials in this series are arranged chronologically. The ledger contained in Folder 12 was kept by Emma Thoma until William Benshoff became a partner, at which time he began to record stock information in the ledger.
  - Various accounts, 1911/12, 1922, 1931, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ledger, 1922-1925? (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Statistical data, 1930-1943 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Profit and loss statements, (1940-1942)-1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous, 1929-1949 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1930-1962; VI.
  Series VI includes letters received from DuPont, Main and Company (accountants), and dentists using Vernon-Benshoff products. The materials are housed in one folder and are arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Letters Received, 1930-1962 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Publications, 1936-1956; VII.
  Series VII is divided into three subseries, Publications by Vernon-Benshoff Company, Publications about Vernon-Benshoff Company, and Publications on techniques used by other companies. The first subseries contains promotional pamphlets created by the company as well as a run of The Vernonite Work Bench, a monthly publication produced by Vernon-Benshoff which reported on company research. The publication lasted until 1950, when budgetary constraints caused its suspension. The materials in this subseries are arranged chronologically. The second subseries contains articles and reprints from Modern Plastics and Rohm Haas Reporter on Vernon-Benshoff products such as methacrylate resins and other acrylics. The materials in this subseries are arranged chronologically as well. The third subseries consists of reprints from the Journal of American Dentistry which describe research conducted by other companies in the area of dental practices and products. These reprints are arranged chrnologically.
  - Publications by Vernon-Benshoff Company, 1938-1956; 1.
    - Promotional pamphlets, 1938-1956 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - The Vernonite Work Bench, October 1942-September/October 1950 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
  - Publications about Vernon-Benshoff Company, 1936-1950; 2.
    - Modern Plastics, November 1936 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Reprints--"Embedded in Acrylic," from Modern Plastics and "Captured in Castings," from Rohm Hass Reporter, February 1948 and November/December 1950 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Publications on techniques used by other companies, 1932, 1934; 3.
    - Reprints from Journal of American Dental Association, 1932, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Memorabilia, 1941-1953; VIII.
  Series VIII contains a variety of materials which include a safety record certificate, "Camcar Camara" with a picture of embedded acrylic decorating the lobby of Camcar Screw Mfg. Corporation, and a death announcement for employee William E. Williams.
  - Memorabilia, 1941-1953 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Photographs, ca. 1922-1956; IX.
  Series IX, Photographs, contains numerous photographs arranged according to subject matter. The first grouping includes images of laboratory equipment, manufacturing and packaging activities, and microscope photographs of alloys. Another group consists of interior and exterior shots of the Vernon-Benshoff Company, while a third includes employees, conventions, and demonstrations. The final group contains photographs of objects in acrylic.
  - Laboratory equipment, manufacturing and packaging, microscope photos of alloys (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Interiors and exteriors of Vernon-Benshoff Company (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Employees, conventions, demonstrations (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Objects in acrylic (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Miscellaneous Writings, ca. 1970-1972; X.
  Series X includes various parables, verbal sketches, etc., written by Harold M. Vernon from 1970 to approximately 1972.
  - Vernon, Harold M. Miscellaneous Writings, ca. 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 27)